<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Gouthaman Balaraman</title><link href="http://gouthamanbalaraman.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://gouthamanbalaraman.com/feeds/finance.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://gouthamanbalaraman.com/</id><updated>2015-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>How to Build a Fundamental Factor Model</title><link href="http://gouthamanbalaraman.com/blog/build-fundamental-factor-model.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-06-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Gouthaman Balaraman</name></author><id>tag:gouthamanbalaraman.com,2015-06-22:blog/build-fundamental-factor-model.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a multi-factor model, the return of a stock can be broken out 
into multiple factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ r_i = \alpha_i + \sum_{j=1}{K} \beta_{ij} f_j + \epsilon_i $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The term $\epsilon_i$ is the error term which is assumed to have a 
distribution with zero mean. Now we can write the average return as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ E(r_i) = E(\alpha_i) + \sum_{j=1}{K} \beta_{ij} E(f_j) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be expressed concisely using the matrix representation:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ r_i = \mathbf{\beta}^T_i \mathbf{f}  + \epsilon_i $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\begin{eqarray}
\mathbf{\beta}&lt;em i1="i1"&gt;i &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; (\alpha_i, \beta&lt;/em&gt;, \beta_{i2}, ..., \beta_{iK})^T \ 
\mathbf(f) &amp;amp;=&amp;amp; (1, f_1, f_2, ..., f_K)^T
\end{eqarray}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using this notation, the average return can then be written as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ E(r_i) = \mathbf{\beta}_i^T E(\mathbf{f}) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see that the average return on the stock is the product of factor exposures ($\mathbf{\beta}_i$) and factor premium ($\mathbf{f}$). In a fundamental factor model, the &lt;em&gt;factor exposures&lt;/em&gt;  are characteristics of an investment (such as a stock) that is known, such as the Price to Earnings ratio, or momentum of the stock, or market capitalization. The &lt;em&gt;factor premium&lt;/em&gt; is the unknown that we wish to determine empirically. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the tenets of quantitative portfolio management is:
&lt;em&gt;the average return of an investment is the payoff
for taking risk&lt;/em&gt;. The risk of a stock has two components:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Total Risk = Non-Diversifiable Risk + Diversifiable Risk&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Risk can be measured using the variance of the returns:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V(r_i) = V(\alpha + \beta_{i1}f_1 + ... + \beta_{iK}f_K) + V(\epsilon_i) + V(\epsilon_i)$$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be expressed in the matrix notation as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ V(r_i) = \mathbf{\beta}_i^T V(\mathbf{f}) \mathbf{\beta}_i + V(\epsilon_i) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where $V(\mathbf{f})$ is a $(K+1) \times (K+1)$-dimensional variance-covariance matrix. The diversifiable component which an investor can mitigate by diversification
is the term $V(\epsilon_i)$. The non-diversifiable componenent which the market 
rewards is obtained from factor exposures $\mathbf{\beta}_i$ and factor premium
risk $V(\mathbf{f})$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparatory Work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a series of steps that one has to do before we can run a 
multi-variable regression to determine the factor premiums. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Choosing the factors&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to choose the factors that we wish to include in the model. This step 
is usually driven by the intuition an investor has on the market, and 
characteristics of the stock that are important. For instance, some fundamental factors that would make sense for equity investments include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Valuation Factors&lt;/em&gt;: Market capitalization (size), price-to-book ratio (P/B),
price-to-earnings ratio (P/E), price-to-sales ratio (P/S).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solvency Factors&lt;/em&gt;: Debt-to-equity ratio (D/E), current ratio (CUR, a metric
of short term solvency), interest coverage ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Growth Potential Factors&lt;/em&gt;: Capital-expenditure-to-sales ratio, R&amp;amp;D-expenditure-to-sales ratio, advertising-expenditure-to-sales ratio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technical factors&lt;/em&gt;: Momentum, trading volume, short interest shares shorted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Analyst factors&lt;/em&gt;: Analyst rating changes, earnings revision etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly some fundamental factors that would make sense for fixed income investments 
include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Credit Factors&lt;/em&gt;: Credit quality, different vendor ratings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Interest Rate Sensitivity Factors&lt;/em&gt;: Effective duration, key rate duration at
various tenors, convexity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Asset Type Factors&lt;/em&gt;: Some factors can be asset specific, such as:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Municipals&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State or issuer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purpose such as revenue or general obligation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mortgages&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coupon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Amortization type&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Issuer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Treatment of the Risk-Free Rate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we are building a model to measure the payoff for undertaking risk, it is
conventional to subtract the risk-free rate from the returns of the investment. The
rational is that the risk-free rate is the return that can be obtained on any
investment without any risk. In order to do this, we need to define what is
considered risk-free. In the U.S. markets, the U.S. treasury bills are used
as a proxy for the risk free rate. In other markets, one has to exercise care
in identifying a risk free rate. All sovereign bond/bill  rates do not 
immediately translate into risk-free rates because a lot of countries (developing 
and developed) have risk of default as well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the risk-free rate $r_{ft}$ has been identified, the excess return can be defined
as &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ r*&lt;em it="it"&gt;{it} = r&lt;/em&gt; - r_{ft} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Building the Data Sample&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... to be continued&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="finance"></category></entry></feed>